Register of the John Barron papers
Hoover Institution Archives
John Barron papers
1927-1996
98020
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, notes, speeches and writings, and photographs, relating to Morris Childs, Federal Bureau of Investigation informant within the Communist Party of the United States; Federal Bureau of Investigation surveillance of the Communist Party; and the relationship between the Communist Party of the United States and the Soviet communist party and government. Includes some papers of Morris Childs. Used as research material for the book by John Barron, Operation Solo: The FBI's Man in the Kremlin (Washington, D.C., 1996).
Barron, John, 1930-2005
Access
Collection open for research.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (2 reels).
Related Collection
Morris Childs, Hoover Institution Archives
Scope and Content
The documents of this collection were selected by JOHN BARRON (b. 1930), American journalist and author, to be used as research material for his book Operation SOLO: The FBI Man in the Kremlin (Washington, D.C.: Regnery Pub., 1996). The book describes an operation (later called SOLO) conducted by the FBI in 1954-1982. The main character in the operation was Morris Childs (1902-1991), a prominent member of the Communist Party USA (CPUSA), who enjoyed absolute trust of communist leaders both in the United States and the Soviet Union.
Morris Childs, along with his brother Jack Childs and wife Eva Childs, made fifty-seven trips (called by the FBI "missions") to the Soviet Union and other countries of the socialist camp. Morris Childs often accompanied Gus Hall, General Secretary of the CPUSA; sometimes he traveled alone or with his wife. Morris had conferences with party leaders in the countries he visited and was shown confidential and secret documents.
Within Operation SOLO the FBI supported a clandestine communication system designed and built by the Soviet KGB (Committee for State Security). Through this system the FBI regularly received messages from the Kremlin and, in the name of Jack or Morris, sent back information the United States wanted the Soviets to get. The FBI also handled millions of dollars smuggled from the Soviet Union to New York, either by Jack or Morris or by KGB agents, for the CPUSA.
The collection is divided into four series. Of most interest is the SUBJECT FILE series, which reflects the activities of Gus Hall, General Secretary of the CPUSA, and gives an insight into Operation SOLO and how it was handled by the KGB. It also includes descriptions of communication devices, decoding tables, pictures of KGB agents in New-York, etc. The WRITINGS and CORRESPONDENCE series document John Barron's work on the book.
Childs, Morris, 1902-1991; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Kommunisticheskai͡a partii͡a Sovetskogo Soi͡uza.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation.; Communism--United States.; Communism.; Internal security--United States.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union.; United States--Politics and government.
- WRITINGS, 1995
  Scope and Contents note
  John Barron's notes, and reviews of his book Operation SOLO: The FBI Man in the Kremlin, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Notes, holograph and typescripts, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Reviews, 1995 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1992-1996
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Boyle?, Walter, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Childs, Eva, 1994 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Fees, James Richard, 1996 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Klehr, Harvey, 1992 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Langtry?, John, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Sessions, William, 1995 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Wannall, W. Raymond, 1996 (Box-folder 1: 9)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1934-1989
  Correspondence, essays, pamphlets, clippings, bulletins, appeals, instructions, leaflets, minutes, lists, memoranda, prospectus, press interview, radio address, outlines, reports, notes, press releases, speeches, and questionnaire, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Carr, Sam, 1938 and 1989 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Chinese-Soviet relations. See Soviet-Chinese relation (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Communist Party of the Soviet Union (Kommunisticheskaia Partiia Sovetskogo Soiuza), 1959-1975
    - General, 1966 and 1975 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Congresses, 1959 and 1971
      - Twenty-First Congress, Includes speeches of A. N. Shelepin, N. S. Khrushchev, Chou En-lai, and Leonid I. Brezhnev, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 12)
      - Twenty-Fourth Congress, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Communist Party USA
    - General, Includes CPUSA anti-war leaflets and a list of members of the Central Committee CPUSA in 1934, 1934 and 1952-1971 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Campaign of Morris Childs for the US Senate, Includes Earl Browder's press interview and radio address, 1938 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Links with foreign communist parties, 1940-1977
      - General, 1964-1967 (Box-folder 1: 16)
      - Communist Party of the Soviet Union (Kommunisticheskaia partiia Sovetskogo Soiuza), 1940-1977 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Hall, Gus, 1964-1965
    - Correspondence, 1964-1965.
      - Brezhnev, Leonid I., undated (Box-folder 1: 18)
      - Castro, Fidel, 1964 (Box-folder 1: 19)
      - Communist Party of Czechoslovakia, Central Committee (Ceskoslovenska Komunisticka Strana, Ustredni Vybor), undated (Box-folder 1: 20)
      - Communist Party of the Soviet Union (Kommunisticheskaia Partiia Sovetskogo Soiuza), undated (Box-folder 1: 21)
      - Johnson, Beatrice, 1965 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Reports
      - Undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
      - 1974 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Jews - Soviet Union, undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Operation SOLO, Includes a letter from J. Edgar Hoover and descriptions of SOLO missions and communications, 1952-1976 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Soviet-Chinese relations, (some documents in Russian or Chinese), 1963-1967 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, undated
  108 prints, including of Morris and Eva Childs, Gus Hall, KPSS leaders, and FBI agents
  - 29 prints selected by John Barron for his book (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - 23 prints depicting Morris Childs and 7 prints depicting Eva Childs alone or with other people (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - 20 prints depicting Gus Hall alone or with the leaders of the KPSS and other people (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - 19 prints, Includes prints of KPSS leaders (Khrushchev, Brezhnev, Suslov, etc.) (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - 10 prints, Includes prints of FBI agents who participated in Operation SOLO (Box-folder 2: 11)